Guide to the William Heyen Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- January 2010 Acquisition, 1961-2009; 4; (13 boxes)
  - Writings, 2005-2009
    - Annotated Books
      - Tall, Deborah. From Where We Stand: Recovering a Sense of Place (Box 40)
        Page 241 and the back flyleaf contain the beginnings of poems that, as Heyen notes, became poems from Crazy Horse in Stillness.
      - Tanahashi, Kazuaki. Essential Zen (Box 40)
        This book contains drafts of unpublished poems and some notes on a pig note about the moon in the river that appeared in Pig Notes & Dumb Music.
      - Teale, Edwin Way. A Naturalist Buys an Old Farm (Box 41)
        Laid in are the drafts of what never became a section of The Chestnut Rain, about a chestnut sill Teale mentions.
      - Trevelyan, George and Belle Valerie Gaunt. A Tent in Which to Pass a Summer Night (Box 41)
        This book contains the first drafts of "Easter Morning," which appeared in Shoah Train: Poems, and of the pig note that concludes Pig Notes & Dumb Music.
      - Van Der Post, Laurens. The Voice of the Thunder (Box 41)
        This book contains two unpublished poem drafts.
      - Wagner, Gottfried. Twilight of the Wagners: The Unveiling of a Family's Legacy (Box 41)
        This book contains the first drafts of the poems "Zeitpost," "Kindred Spirits," and "The Key" which will appear in Shoah Train.
      - Wiesenthal, Simon. The Sunflower (Box 41)
        Heyen's responses are written on pages 99-100 and 208.
      - Williamson, Chilton. Roughnecking It (Box 41)
        This book contains the first drafts of 2-3 poems that appeared in Crazy Horse in Stillness (1996).
      - Worth, C. Brooke. Of Mosquitoes, Moths, and Mice (Box 41)
        This book contains the first drafts of the poem "Egg."
      - Zassenhaus, Hiltgunt. Walls: Resisting the Third Reich—One Woman's Story (Box 41)
        An unpublished poem is written on the back flyleaf.
      - Zweig, Paul. Walt Whitman: the Making of the Poet (Box 41)
        This book's back flyleaves contain the first drafts of an unpublished poem Heyen spent many years revising: "The Fountain Pen: An Autobiography."
  - Journals (bound and published copies), 1965-2008
    Included are bound copies of original journals held by the Rare Books and Special Collections, University of Rochester and which have been published as The Cabin: Journal 1964-1985, copies of which are also included.
    - Journal no. 1, 1965-1974 (Box 42)
    - Journal no. 2, 1975-1980 (Box 42)
    - Journal no. 3, 1980-1981 (Box 42)
    - Journal no. 4, 1982-1983 (Box 42)
    - Journal no. 5, 1983-1984 (Box 42)
    - Journal no. 6, 1984-1985 (Box 42)
    - Journal no. 7, 1985 Jan-Jun (Box 42)
    - The Cabin: Journal 1964-1985, 2 copies, 2008; 2 (Box 42)
  - Collaboration with Robert E. Marx, 2003-2008
    Includes material relating to a planned limited-edition book, A Poetics of Hiroshima: Two Poems by William Heyen & 12 Etchings by Robert Marx, to have been printed by Terence Chouniard at Wells College and under the imprint of The Black Bird Press, Marx's press with which he published collaborations with Daniel Berrigan, Elizabeth Bishop, Milton Kessler, and other poets. Material includes correspondence, manuscripts, proofs, and 17 etchings signed by Marx.
    - Marx Project, circa 2007-2008 (Box 43)
    - Printed material, "Considering the Voluntary Absence of God", 2003 (Box 43)
    - Correspondence, 2006-2008; 3 (Box 43)
    - A Poetics of Hiroshima with Marx etchings, circa 2007-2008 (Box 43)
    - A Poetics of Hiroshima, 2008 (Box 43)
    - Etchings signed by Robert Marx (Box 44)
  - Oversize
    - SUNY Brockport basketball photo (from Correspondence), 1961 (Box 44)